<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great duty of love and faithfulness to our native country occasion'd by the coolness of some in its necessary defence, and the forwardness of others, in pushing on its ruine / deliver'd in a sermon at the Chappel of Popler, December 3, 1693, by Josiah Woodward ...</title>
            <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38760</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18111191</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18111191</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106807</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67014)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106807)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1113:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great duty of love and faithfulness to our native country occasion'd by the coolness of some in its necessary defence, and the forwardness of others, in pushing on its ruine / deliver'd in a sermon at the Chappel of Popler, December 3, 1693, by Josiah Woodward ...</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Simpson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Publish'd at the request of the hearers."</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXII, 8-9 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Patriotism --  England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106807:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106807:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Great Duty OF <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> TO OUR Native Country: OCCASION'D By the Coolneſs of Some in its Neceſſary DEFENCE, and the Forwardneſs of Others, in puſhing on its Ruine. Deliver'd in A SERMON AT THE CHAPPEL of <hi>POPLER, December</hi> 3. 1693.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd at the Requeſt of the Hearers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSIAH WOODWARD</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Popler.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Neſcio qua Natale Solum Dulcedine cunctos Ducit, &amp; im memores non ſinit eſſe ſui.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Simpſon</hi> at the Harp in St. <hi>Pauls-Church-Yard,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106807:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106807:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To my</hi> Country-Men, <hi>the Coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Souldiers and Sea-Men of</hi> England, <hi>in the Service of Their Moſt Excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, King</hi> WILLIAM <hi>and Queen</hi> MARY.</head>
            <p>TO whom may I ſo fitly Dedicate this ſhort Diſcourſe, concerning <hi>Love and Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to our Native Country,</hi> as to You, Gentlemen, who are (under the Divine Providence) the Bullwarks and Ramparts of it. We have but few ſtrong Garriſons, ſave what are lodged in our Wooden Caſtles floating on the Sea: And we hope that theſe, together with our Land-Forces Headed by ſo brave a General, will (with Gods Bleſſing) keep the Land of our Nativity from being the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Seat of War and Miſery; and make it at laſt a Scene of Triumph and Peace.</p>
            <p>Our Engliſh Arms by Sea and Land, have been famed and feared all over the World within a few years paſt; and many of you give us the happy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration,
<pb facs="tcp:106807:3"/> that all our Engliſh Valour is not withered. But there is one thing too ſadly, and alas! too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally forgotten, though it be very neceſſary both to True Valour and Good Succeſs; and that is, True Piety.</p>
            <p>We cannot but own, That there is a Holy and Almighty God, the Diſpoſer of all Events: How much does it concern us then, to ſecure an Ally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with him, that he appear not againſt us! For he is the Lord of Hoſts, and will appear on one ſide or the other, where Armies engage; and what Part ſoever he takes, it will be ſure to be Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious: <hi>It is God that girdeth me with ſtrength,</hi> ſaid Valiant <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 18. 32. He is the God of the Spirits of all Men, and can either advance them to an unſurmountable Height of Valour, or ſink them to a baſe and contemptible feebleneſs and fear.</p>
            <p>No Souldier therefore marches in ſo good Array, as he that is girt with <hi>the whole Armour of God,</hi> mentioned <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 11. and hath <hi>the Praiſes of God in his Mouth,</hi> as well as a <hi>Two-edg'd Sword in his hand,</hi> Pſal. 149. 6. <hi>Goliath,</hi> the Champion of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> wanted no Weapon nor Strength of Arm; but he came forth defying God, and ſo he blaſphemed himſelf to death, and fell by the ſling of a deſpiſed Stripling.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106807:3"/>
            <p> Wherefore, as you would approve your ſelves great and brave Men, labour to gain the Victory over baſe and ſhameful Vices. Your Victory here will be a moſt happy <hi>Preſage</hi> of the Fall of all your other Enemies that riſe up againſt you: For even Death it ſelf will become your Conqueſt <hi>through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me therefore entreat you, <hi>My Brethren,</hi> with the moſt Affectionate Bowels of a Friend and Brother, That you keep the fear of God before your eyes, and call devoutly on his Glorious and Fearful Name. And ſince you have not often fit places of retired Prayer, be the more frequent and earneſt in ſhort Ejaculations at all times. Let not the Fury of any Lust or Paſſion make you forget God, in whoſe hands your breath is, and whoſe Bleſſing alone can make you proſperous. Conſider therefore what a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it is, to be accuſtomed to that common, but dreadful ſin, of Swearing and Damning. 'Tis a ſin of no Temptation, but of infinite Guilt, ſo that it ſeems to need no Argument to induce a Souldier to leave it, but to conſider, that it is Fighting under the Devil without Pay, and that againſt an Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent GOD, who will deſtroy his Enemies eternally.</p>
            <p>Be entreated alſo to keep strict ſobriety, or you cannot be Men, much leſs Heroes: And be just,
<pb facs="tcp:106807:4"/> civil and modeſt, in your Deportment, or you will want the hraveſt Method of Conquering, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all People over to your ſide. And when you come to face your Enemies, let Love, Honour and Concern for your GOD, and King, your Religion and Countrey, make you Reſolute and Couragious: And let not Deſpair it ſelf encline you to turn your Backs, for then you give opportunity to the veriest Coward to kill you without danger; the greateſt Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is ever made in the Purſuit.</p>
            <p>In a word, I beſeech the Invincible God to lead you on inſpirited with true Gallantry, and to bring you back laden with the ſpoils of your Enemys; that ſo our lateſt Posterity may Crown you with Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Honour, as the Preſervers (under God) of our Lives, Liberties, and Religion; and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors of our moſt Deſperate and Dangerous Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So Prays <hi>Your Servant and Country-Man</hi> J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106807:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 122. 8, 9.</bibl>
                  <p>For my Brethren and Companions ſake, I will now ſay, Peace be within thee.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe of the Houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek thy Good.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT was to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that theſe kind Wiſhes are Voted in the Text. And indeed, to what Place ſhould a <hi>Jew</hi> wiſh ſo well as to his own Land? for which the ſcatter'd Remnant of them do yet retain an inextinguiſhable Love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was at that time both the Metropolitan Church and City of <hi>Judea:</hi> and in this double Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> here (inſpired by the Spirit of God) demonſtrates his Zeal for its Peace and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity; as the words diſtinctly expreſs. <hi>For my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Companions ſake I will now ſay, Peace be within thee.</hi> That is, I wiſh Thee all deſirable Bleſſings, O my Native Country, for the ſake of my Relations and Friends who live in thee. And that which fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther engages my Concern for thy Welfare is, that God hath Choſen <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to be the Seat of his Holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. There the true God was then Worſhipt, and there was his Church and peculiar People: therefore I will do all that in me lyes to Advance thy Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106807:5"/> 
               <hi>Becauſe of the Houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek thy Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, in theſe words we find two very conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Reaſons for the Love of our Country, which muſt needs be binding to ſuch as have either Senſe or Conſcience. For</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> If we have any bowels of Humanity towards our Relations which are our own Fleſh, or to our Dear Friends, which are as our own Soul: we muſt ſeek the Peace and Proſperity of the place of their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation: and ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>For my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> &amp;c. Or</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If we have any pious Concern for the Sacred Intereſts of the reformed Religion, and the Church of God: we muſt ſeek the Good of this our Land; as in the latter part of the Text<hi>—Becauſe of the Houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek thy Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words then tend to impreſs a Zealous and Indefatigable Concern for the common Good upon our Conſciences: aſſuring us of this point of Doctrine:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> That it is a neceſſary part of our Duty, both as Men and Chriſtians, to promote the juſt intereſts of our Country in Church and State.</p>
            <p>Both theſe Sorts of Intereſts, were ever eſteemed by the Heathen as their moſt pretious and even vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Enjoyments; and they thought the Defence of them, the moſt juſt and neceſſary Cauſes of War: which ever awaken'd all their Courage and Zeal to aſſert and defend. When they fought <hi>Pro aris &amp; Focis,</hi> (as they term'd it) that is, For their Altars and Fire places, they ſtill fought with a pertinacious Reſolution to Conquer or Dye. And theſe are the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106807:5"/> very Things expreſt in the Text before us: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are the Things which we contend for in the preſent War with <hi>France:</hi> which is endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not only to get our Houſes, but the Houſes of our God into their poſſeſſion. And how they will then treat them, we may ſee by the Ruines of the Proteſtant Churches in <hi>France.</hi> There were there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few years, more than a Thouſand places of God's Publick Worſhip, where above Fifteen Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thouſand Proteſtants ſerved God according to his own Inſtitution. <note n="*" place="margin">According to the computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Carlot,</hi> the Deputy of <hi>Levennes,</hi> in their laſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Synod, at <hi>Loudun.</hi>
               </note> But alas! the Popiſh Fury has either layd thoſe Churches in Ruinous Heaps, or ſo Fundamentally deſtroy'd them, that there's no Token that they ever were in Being.</p>
            <p>And alas! they have treated the poor Proteſtants as barbarouſly, as they have done their Churches, as the Deaths of many Martyrs and Confeſſors there, by unexampled Crueltys do abundantly teſtify.</p>
            <p>They have diſ-joynted all the Bones of ſome by Skrews faſten'd to every Finger and Toe. They have broyled Others before ſlow Fires. They have rolled the naked Bodies of Others upon broken pieces of Glaſs, till there was no room for any more to pierce the miſerable Sufferers. They have kept ſome from Sleep many Dayes and Nights together to diſtract them, and kept otherſome from Food as long to Starve them; As thoſe Authors of undoubted Fidelity, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Claud</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Jurieu,</hi> have publickly te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified: together with many other Relations too ſad to be read without Tears, or conſider'd without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of Pain in all tender Bowels. And if any yet doubt of this, let them look on thoſe excellent Men,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106807:6"/> who for the ſake of the Proteſtant Religion, are at this Day Chained in the <hi>French-Gallies,</hi> with a chain of more than Fifty pounds weight. And to this Day we ever and anon hear of an Aſſembly of Proteſtants there, taken and hang'd, for no other reaſon, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are found at their Prayers together.</p>
            <p>Now, when all theſe Miſeryes are advancing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Borders; When the ſame infernal Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons (blooded by the Executions, and hardened by the Groans of their own Country-Men) are longing to try our Conſtancy by the ſame Methods. What reaſon have we to ſtand up as one man in the juſt Defence of our Lives and Liberties, and the neceſſary Vindication of our Religion and Country? What Spirit are they of, that will not Act in their own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt <hi>Cut-Throats</hi> and Robbers of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?</p>
            <p>When <hi>Joab,</hi> the General of the Armies of <hi>Iſrael</hi> fought againſt the <hi>Syrians</hi> and <hi>Ammonites:</hi> He exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Valour of his Soldiers to a wonder, with that ſhort ſpeech of his (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 12.) <hi>Be of good Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and let us play the Men for our People and the Citys of our God.</hi> And the bare mentioning of theſe dear enjoyments, inſpired them with Valour to ſuch a Degree, that they got an intire Victory over their Enemies that had encloſed them round.</p>
            <p>And this ſuggeſtion was ever a part of the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Heathen Officers before they engaged their Enemies: Namely, To mind their Soldiers, that they were to Fight for their <hi>Temples and Fire-ſides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it uſually excited them to put themſelves out to the utmoſt; and to count their Lives as nothing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106807:6"/> in compariſon with that for which they adventured them.</p>
            <p>And is it poſſible that Chriſtians can ſink below the Honour and Honeſty of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> in this point? Would a <hi>Heathen</hi> adventure his life in the moſt threatning dangers to defend his Country? And can any Chriſtian be ſo baſe, as to hazzard his life to Betray his Country? Alas! any but <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> may well make a doubt of this. And ſurely all the World may well ſtand amazed at our Coldneſs in our neceſſary Vindication of all that can be accounted Dear to us. But above all, they that have felt the <hi>French</hi> Barbarityes, muſt needs wonder at the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Practiſes of thoſe people who can find in their hearts to befriend the Deſignes of ſuch an Enemy.</p>
            <p>It is indeed, the moſt unnatural betraying of the Eſſential Intereſts of our Country, that makes a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this Nature ſeaſonable: which one would hardly believe, (were it only for the Honour of our Nation, and humane Nature) did we not know it by too ſad and coſtly experience. In truth, this degenerate age abounds with monſters of Sin of all kinds: men are monſtrous in their ſins againſt God, by bold and pleading Atheiſm: againſt their own Souls by dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful imprecations of Damnation: and againſt their own Country, not only by Treachery and Correſpondence with its fatal Enemies, but even by offering earneſt Prayers and Vows for their Succeſſes; and diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Grinning Curſed Laughter</hi> at the loſſes of their own Nation. An Affront which no Government in the world has leſs deſerved by any Severities to them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106807:7"/> than this, and none upon earth but this, would bear at their Hands.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore in oppoſition to the common per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſs to the Intereſts of our Country, and their own in the end (notwithſtanding all their chimeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal fancies to the contrary) endeavor to aſſert theſe two Poſitions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That we are bound by the Laws of God and Nature to advance the Intereſts of our Church and Nation: or, as the Text expreſſes it, to pray for the publick <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>ſeek</hi> the common <hi>Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That no perſonal or particular Reſpects can take off this double obligation.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Poſ.</hi> That we are bound by the Laws of God and Nature to pray for the publick <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>ſeek</hi> the common <hi>Good.</hi> Indeed, the genuine Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are the moſt univerſal and indelible Laws of our Creator. And amongſt theſe, there are none more deeply impreſt than thoſe of Self-love, and a Deſire of Self-preſervation: which ever make the feebleſt and fearfulleſt Creatures put themſelves out <hi>(Ad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremum Virium)</hi> even beyond their uſual ſtrength. Now, if I would preſerve my being, I muſt have a place to ſubſiſt in, and means of Subſiſtence. And this will put us on the defence of our Native Land, to whoſe common Comforts we have a natural Right, and it a Right to our continual aſſiſtance. And the grater Eaſe, Liberty, and Safety, I enjoy in my own Country; my Love and Concern for the Defence of it againſt its Enemies, muſt in reaſon proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably increaſe. If I am born a Free-man, I may juſtly withſtand ſuch as come to load me with Chains.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106807:7"/> Reaſon will ſoon agree with that advice of the Holy Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 21. <hi>If thou mayeſt be free, chooſe it rather, than to live a Bond-ſlave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, the Love of my Country is as natural as Self-love, and this as natural as our Breath, or Pulſe. And all ſober Heathens have ever been true to this Principle of Nature: inſomuch, that we hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find any Maxime ſo Celebrated amongſt them as that Epidemical one, <hi>Dulce eſt pro Patriâ mori.</hi> That is, It is a ſweet thing to Dye for ones Country. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more Common than ſuch expreſſions in <hi>Cicero, Seneca,</hi> and all their Philoſophers: And nothing more frequent than inſtances of it in <hi>Livy, Tacitus,</hi> and all their Hiſtorians.</p>
            <p>When it was told the Romans by their <hi>Augures,</hi> that their State would never flouriſh, till ſome Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Noble Blood leapt into the great <hi>Chaſm</hi> at <hi>Rome:</hi> with what Chearfulneſs and Bravery did the Noble <hi>Curtius</hi> mount his Steed and leap down the precipice! When <hi>Attilius Regulus</hi> was taken Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by the publick Enemy, and by them permitted to return to <hi>Rome</hi> upon his parole of Honour: and there perceiv'd that the State could not condeſcend to their demands for His Ranſome without their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; He not only diſſwaded the Senate from procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Liberty at ſuch a Rate, but ſecretly went and offerd himſelf to his Enemies, and there under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went a moſt painful and lingering Death, rather than be an occaſion of any detriment to his Country by his Life.</p>
            <p>And theſe Illuſtrious Inſtances of Zeal for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good were not ſo much gazed at in thoſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106807:8"/> dayes (as we do now, in the Hiſtory of them) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were then common, and every Body thought it their bounden Duty. For their uſual diſcourſe was, <hi>Nemo ſibi naſcitur, Partem Patria, partem Parentes, partem Amici poſtulant.</hi> That is, None of us is born for himſelf; Our Country and our Parents, and Friends, may ſo duly challenge a part of us, that we cannot look on our ſelves as at our own diſpoſal, but as conſecrated to the common Good. So that theſe honeſt Heathens following the Light of Nature, and the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in the text guided by revelation, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the ſame Leader, that is God; and in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the King of Nations, they pray'd for, fought for, and dy'd for their Country.<hi>—For my Brethren and Companions ſake, I will ſay</hi> (that is, I will pray) that Peace (that is, all manner of Bleſſings) may <hi>be within thee,</hi> O my deſirable Country. <hi>Peace be within thy Walls, and Proſperity within thy Pallaces,</hi> ver. 7. may they <hi>Proſper that love thee,</hi> ver. 6. But <hi>let them all be Confounded</hi> (in their Deſignes) <hi>and turn'd back that hate</hi> Zion: Let them be <hi>as Graſs upon the Houſe tops, which withereth before it groweth up,</hi> Pſal. 129. 5, 6.</p>
            <p>Nothing can be more exaſperating to human Bowels than to ſee our Parents, or Brethren, or Wives, or Children ſlayn before our Eyes. To ſee them wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in their precious blood, which by ſympathy of Nature we look on as our own. To ſee our Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes plunder'd, and afterwards burnt. To behold li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious Soldiers treating Age with Scorn, and Youth with ſhame. O dreadful! What ſenſible Soul can lend a hand, to draw on ſuch a heavy Chain of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106807:8"/> which we nor our Poſterity are able to bear?</p>
            <p>Yet further, there is in men a ſort of natural ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs for the Reſt of the bones and duſt of their deceaſed Anceſtors. How can I chooſe but be ſad, ſayd <hi>Nehemia, when the Place of my Fathers Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres lyeth waſte?</hi> Neh. 2. 3. There is alſo a natural Love to our Poſterity, which is very forcible. And nothing can touch a Parents Heart with more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Regret, than to behold the ſymptoms of the Miſeries of their Poſterity.</p>
            <p>And Chriſtianity Cheriſhes and Enforces all theſe honeſt Inſtincts of Nature. For our bleſſed Saviour came not to deſtroy theſe Laws, but to perfect and ſublimate them. And his Goſpel declares, thoſe worſe than Infidels, that <hi>provide not for thoſe of their own Houſe,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 8. So that we have Super-abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant obligations to be fathful to our Countries Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts.</p>
            <p>Now, without all controverſie, we have manifeſt reaſon to expect the greateſt Violences in all theſe reſpects from our Enemies of <hi>France,</hi> if they prevail over us, which God of his infinite goodneſs avert. They waſte with Fire and Sword the moſt Famous and Antient Cities, and their Inhabitants: As in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> and other Countries. They pull the very bones of Princes out of their Sepulchres, and will not ſuffer their Duſt to reſt: As in the Caſe of the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Princes buryed at <hi>Hydelberg.</hi> They take little Children from their natural Parents to breed them up in their own Superſtitions: as they have dealt by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Proteſtant Families in <hi>France.</hi> So that there can hardly be imagined any Plague ſo univerſally calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106807:9"/> to the preſent and ſucceding Ages, as a <hi>French</hi> Conqueſt would be: nor can people act more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanly and unchriſtianly than in helping on ſuch a Calamity.</p>
            <p>And this barbarity of deſerting and betraying our Country will be further aggravated, if we conſider: That as the undutifulneſs of a child to a Parent, is mightily blacken'd by the Conſideration of the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary goodneſs and indulgence of the Parent; ſo is the un-natural Treachery of Engliſh-men to their Mother Country, in that they Betray a good Land, abounding with all uſefull accomodations, and with peculiar Liberty and Light of God's Word, which are the ſweeteſt enjoyments of humane Life: in which the happineſs of no people upon Earth is parallel to ours.</p>
            <p>O ſad! Do the Miſeries of ſuch a Land, and the Loſs of ſuch enjoyments deſerve the <hi>Grinning Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of any amongſt us? Can there be found in a Chriſtian Land ſuch a ſeed of <hi>Nero,</hi> as can rake in the Bowels of ſuch a Mother with delight? Surely Nature and humane Bowels are periſht in ſuch Breaſts. We muſt take Leave to ſpeak plain to theſe things, ſince for ought we know, we ſpeak our laſt: For theſe Treacheries have helpt to caſt us on the very brink of Ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Now, the Inference that is naturally drawn from this firſt Poſition, is That ſuch as any way Contribute to weaken the Defence of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, muſt needs be condemn'd by themſelves and all the World, <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> have ever lookt upon ſuch as the worſt of men, bereaved of all no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106807:9"/> of Good, and ſence of Honour. Yea, what ever the Government or Governours be, the caſe is nothing alter'd. Treaſon againſt the State and a Man's own Land, is ever horrid and abominable; and the very horror of it has made many a man run mad. <note n="*" place="margin">As in the Caſe of one Mr. <hi>C.</hi> a skilful Shipwright ſent into <hi>France</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. to inſtruct them in the building of Ships; who as he was returning home, had ſuch Terrors on his Conſcience that he piſtoled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and never ſet foot on his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Land again, to whoſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts he had been ſo falſe. As an Eye-witneſs now living teſtifies.</note> Such as betray their own Nation are Murtherers of their own Parents, and Brethren, and Children; and do in effect ſet Fire to their own Houſes and Churches; and where the madneſs is ſo extreme, 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if at laſt they murther themſelves.</p>
            <p>And ſuch as any way contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this, take a proportionable ſhare in this horrid Guilt: Such as Embezzle the publick Stores do really rob every particular Perſon in the Nation, who is intereſted therein, and whoſe ſafety depends thereupon. And theſe Publick Cheats, are worſe than Robbers on the High-way.</p>
            <p>Again, to be falſe in any publick Office or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in ſuch a ſeaſon as this, is at once to betray, not only the Intereſts of theſe Three Nations, but of a <hi>Fourth Part of the World:</hi> and whatever kindneſs any one ſhews to the Common Enemy and Invader, is (as ſuch) a real Injury to all Chriſtendom, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the univerſal Empire of <hi>France,</hi> and the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Ruin of other Nations; an extream Guilt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to caſt any ſenſible Perſon into an Agony with the horror of it.</p>
            <p>But perhaps ſom People are by private Reſpects and Opinions drawn into this Snare: and ſo may think to ward off that imputation of Baſeneſs and Treach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106807:10"/> which is layd to their Charge by the Grand Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of our Land, and by the generality of men. Their Pleas will properly fall under the conſideration of my ſecond Poſition; and I think will appear to all conſiderate and equal Judges to fall before it, which was;</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Poſ.</hi> That no perſonal and particular Reſpects can take off our natural and ſupernatural obligation of ſeeking the Good of our Church and Nation.</p>
            <p>Now, this is a Truth as evident, as, That the Whole is greater than its Part: Or, that a Million is more than a ſingle Unite. For even ſo, muſt an univerſal Good of neceſſity be more regardable than a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. This our Reaſon cannot ſo much as queſtion.</p>
            <p>And if it were poſſible, the duty of it would be more clear to a well inform'd Conſcience, than the truth of it to ſound Reaſon. For, what Chriſtian ever yet diſputed, whether the mad Humour of running <note n="*" place="margin">Known to our men in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies;</hi> ſometimes to their Coſt.</note> 
               <hi>Muck</hi> amongſt the Indians, be an execrable Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or not? Where a reſolute Fellow whom they call a <hi>Muck</hi> (madded by diſcontent) does all he can to be the death of all mankind, and uſually begins the Tragedy in the Butchery of his own Family. Now as to our Caſe; tho' we do not act thus with our own hands, yet if we deliberately aſſiſt thoſe that will, it comes all to the ſame End, and we contract the ſame Guilt: For in the Caſe of Murther, all are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals. But yet againſt this, ſome Object.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Obj.</hi> That they have ſuſtained great Loſſes by ſome Alterations in the State, which palls their friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip towards it, and makes them have little Concern for it.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106807:10"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which I Anſwer, that if that Alteration was neceſſary to preſerve the whole Community, every particular Perſon is ſo far from being a Loſer by it, that he hereby gains whatever he enjoys. Perhaps he loſes ſome part of his Eſtate, or ſome place of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: But he enjoys his Life and Liberty, and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Advantages; and all theſe are given to him for a Prey. And he has reaſon not only to be Content, but thankfull: Yea, tho' he had loſt his All in order to the publick Good, and the Happineſs of his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Obj.</hi> But others Clamour, That the preſent Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and Taxes fall heavy, tend to a general pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and make a great Cauſe of diſcontent,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I Anſwer, They cannot move any good or prudent perſon to any impatience: A good man will part with All rather than the Goſpel, as many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have done in all the times of Perſecution. And a prudent man will think a part very profitably layd out to ſave the whole. The preſent Taxes which are deſign'd to proſecute the War againſt the Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, will appear to every conſiderate Perſon as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as a Levy to keep up the Sea-Banks. To be ſparing in a Caſe of ſuch neceſſity, is to be wanting and cruel to our ſelves and Poſterity; like the fatal parſimony of the wealthy Citizens of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who refuſed to lend their own Emperour a Thirtyeth part of that money which the Turkiſh Emperour took from them for a ſpoil, bereaving the wealthyeſt of them of their Lives too, to conſummate the Tragedy.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Obj.</hi> But we reap little advantage by all our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences: ſo that our Contributions ſeem to be expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106807:11"/> for the ſupport of Forreigners, or miſ-employ'd by private hands to their own advantage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We reap the manifeſt advantage of mantaining a brave Fleet at Sea, and a Valiant Army on the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; without which we ſhould in one month be Ruin'd beyond poſſibility of reparation: And all that's done to Support our Allies, tends to find the Enemy work on that ſide, and keeps the War off from us. But if in this Juncture, there appear any amongſt our ſelves ſo vile and proffligate as to embezzle or miſ-imploy the publick Treaſure, they well deſerve, That every Perſon in the three Nations ſhould throw a Stone at them: for every one in this Caſe is an injured perſon.</p>
            <p>But there remains yet a Plea, which would make the betraying of our Country a matter of Conſcience; tho' ſometimes pleaded by thoſe who make Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of nothing. However, they argue thus.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Obj.</hi> Tho' no mans private Intereſts can be pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous enough to weigh down the Intereſts of three Kingdoms lying in the oppoſite Scale; Yet may not our Allegiance ſworn to a diſpoſſeſſed Prince bind us to do all we can for him, let what will follow upon it: tho' it be withal granted, that the ſaid Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prince did induſtriouſly and openly endeavour the <note place="margin">Fiat Juſtitia etſi ruat Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</note> ſubverſion of the Government, and deſtruction of the Community.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is the Goliath-Argument, and like him brings a Sword to cut off its own Head. For, fidelity to God and our Country was our duty before we Swore Allegiance to that Prince, and could not be null'd by the Oath of Allegiance required in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. Yea, the very deſign of binding Subjects
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106807:11"/> by Oath to the Supream Power, is to make it more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Defend (not Deſtroy) the common Good. The fundamental End of all civil Government, being to render the whole Political Body ſafe and happy. And this is plainly affirmed by the Apoſtle, Rom. 13. 4. <hi>The King is God's Miniſter to thee for Good;</hi> that is, in order to the Publick Advantage.</p>
            <p>So then, ſince the Laws of Nature are before and above all political Laws, and we muſt be conſidered as men, before we can fall under the notion of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and ſince Preſervation is the End of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ſince the Laws and Government of <hi>England</hi> have ever conſerved, with the grateſt Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, the Rights and Liberties of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, What Reaſon or Religion can their be in the preſent Caſe? Namely, in making a Sacrifice of our Bibles <note place="margin">Fiat Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia in vastato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Europae, ne ruat Orbis Terrarum.</note> and Mother-Country to the great Golden Image of the <hi>French</hi> Arbitary Power, which the <hi>Babylonians</hi> have ſet up; and would have all People, Nations, and Languages, to fall down and Worſhip it; and they require us, above others, to bow to it, becauſe they make their pretended Kindneſs to the aforeſaid Prince a ſtale to their Ambition and Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>But, can that be indeed an act of Righteouſneſs, which (by humouring the Vice or Error of one man) deſtroys many Millions? Or, is it not rather a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Dementation, than a Principle of Conſcience? For my part, were I diſſatisfy'd about the Legality of the preſent Government, (as I thank God, I am not in the leaſt) yet I ſhould think my ſelf obliged to keep my Scruples private within my own Breaſt. Becauſe if this political notion of mine ſhould in the end prove
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106807:12"/> a groſs miſtake (as our Lawyers, the beſt Caſuiſts in this Caſe, aſſure us it is) what ſhould I have to anſwer for before God and men? When I ſhould be proved to be a fighter againſt the moſt merciful providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God, and a Vile Traytor to my own Country, which is the worſt ſort of Parricide. What Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can a private man make to many injured Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
            <p>It had need be a manifeſt part of Duty, ſo clear and demonſtrative, that there is no room for doubt, that engages us againſt all the Intereſts of this Life: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we ſhall want Comfort in our ſufferings here, and may not only miſs the Crown of Martyrdom in the other world, but fall under the Curſe denounced againſt ſuch as are <hi>without natural affection,</hi> Rom. 1. 31. Yea, ſuch as deny the faith by the want of Chriſtian care <hi>for thoſe of their own Blood,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 8.</p>
            <p>I would therefore ask ſuch Perſons as lye under this unhappy miſtake a few Queſtions; which, ſince Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is pleaded, I would deſire them with due Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Conſcience to conſider:</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is not our Love to our Country, and our Endeavour after the welfare of our Relations and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, a natural binding duty, and in order of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before our engagements to any Political Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is not the Preſervation of the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or whole Political Body, the very End of all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Inſtitutions?</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is it not a contradictions and phrenetick Notion, to deſtroy any Country in Love to the Prince of it, tho' he were never ſo Rightfully entituled to it?</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106807:12"/>
            <p> 4. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Can a Perſon of the Reformed Religion, with a ſafe Conſcience, dip himſelf directly or conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentially, in the Luciferian Deſign of the <hi>French</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, to blot out Proteſtancy, and enſlave Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom?</p>
            <p>5. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Can a good man continue five years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſuch execrable ingratitude to God, as never to render hearty Praiſes to his Great Name, for our Marvelous Deliverance from the Ruine deſigned to our Church and State in the late Reign?</p>
            <p>6. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Can a Papiſt that is Zealous for Popery, even to Bigotry, ſincerely now take, and faithfully keep the Oaths which <hi>Engliſh</hi> Princes are obliged to take at their Coronation?</p>
            <p>7. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Can any good Chriſtian deſire that a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prince, continuing Zealous for the Principles and Propagation of Popery, ſhould again come to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Throne of <hi>England,</hi> and put himſelf afreſh to this hateful and dreadful Dilemma? Namely, either to mock God and men by ſolemn Oaths, and repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Promiſes made to Proteſtants in abominable Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, which was done in the firſt part of a certain Reign: Or to fall down right upon illegal and open Violations of the Rights of the Proteſtants of <hi>England,</hi> as it was done in the laſt part of it.</p>
            <p>If this be allowed, I think we may as well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that a firm Proteſtant may enter upon the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Throne and Chair of the Pope, and Swear and Vow to preſerve all the abominations of the Papacy. But we may eaſily fore-ſee that Papiſts would clamour againſt this as a thing impracticable and ſelf-contradictions: As the Aſſociates of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106807:13"/> Holy League in <hi>France</hi> did againſt their <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, who often proteſted that a Proteſtant was incapable of the <hi>French</hi> Crown; and ſurely we have as much Reaſon to ſay, That a Papiſt is as incapable of the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having conſider'd the two Poſitions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be ſpoken to, I come to Apply them; and the manifeſt Duties which the fore-mentioned things do enforce upon all ſerious Minds, are briefly theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>App.</hi> 1. <hi>Inf.</hi> That we manifeſt our ſelves ſincere Lovers of our Country, by our earneſt Supplications to the Sovereign Diſpoſer of all things, in the behalf of theſe divided Churches and Kingdoms Let us ſay, as the Pſalmiſt in the Text, <hi>Peace be within them.</hi> May all Diviſions and Emnities in Church and State be healed by pacifick Methods, and the Edge of all Paſſion be turn'd againſt that over-grown Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which needs the help of all hands to pull it up. Let us try the powerful Means of Prayer and Faſting, to caſt out that unclean Spirit of Prophaneſs, which has kept ſo long and raving a Poſſeſſion amongſt us. Had our Publick Faſts been kept with better Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, we might have expected to have ſeen our Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Affairs in better Condition. To redreſs this, as much as poſſible, let our private Faſts be very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and very faithful. We have need, alas! to ſet up <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Faſts within our Chambers for three <note place="margin">Dan. 10. 2, 3.</note> Weeks together, without eating any pleaſant Bread, and pray as he does, Dan. 9. 16. <hi>O Lord, according to all thy righteouſneſs, I beſeech thee, let all thine Anger and thy Fury be turn'd away from thy City Jeruſalem, thy holy mountain: becauſe for our Sins and ihe iniquities of</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106807:13"/> 
               <hi>our Fathers,</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>and thy people are become a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to all that are about us.</hi> O, may all the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> never hold their Peace, day nor night, and give the Lord no Reſt, till he eſtabliſh it, and make it a Praiſe in the Earth. <hi>(Iſa.</hi> 62. 6, 7.) Yea, let every Soul endeavour, by his Prayers, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Patriot, by pulling down Bleſſings on his Country. And if we would make way for our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to come before God in an acceptable manner, in the next place,</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Inf.</hi> We muſt, in love to our Country, do all we can towards the removing the general and open Prophaneſs from its Borders; this is the accurſed thing which troubles our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and blaſts our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings. Wickedneſs is a thing which God will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bleſs, and will not long bear. Let us not then be diſcouraged by the Scoffs or Frowns of wicked Men, from endeavouring to proſecute and diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Vice. We cannot well think it a leſs-glorious Martyrdom, to dye for the propagation of the Practiſe of the Goſpel, than for the Profeſſion of its Faith. Let us all then, in our ſtations, endeavour an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Reformation; for, indeed we muſt be look'd on as a Nation under God's Rod, who trys whether leſſer Scourges will bring us to our Duty; and if not, we have reaſon to fear utter Deſtruction. O, that God would give us all a juſt and timely ſenſe of His im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending Wrath, which ſeems to be ſo near, that only the preſent apprehenſions of it can be timely enough to prevent it.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:106807:14"/>
            <p> 3 <hi>Inf.</hi> Let us be ſteddy and vigorous in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of our Duty to Their Majeſties King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY,</hi> to whom, beſides the Tyes of Duty and Gratitude, we are bound by a ſort of Neceſſity, and muſt ſay as in the Text; <hi>For my Brethren and Companions ſakes, I will wiſh your Peace. and becauſe of the Houſes of the Lord our God, we will ſeek your Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4 <hi>Inf.</hi> Let me exhort Souldiers and Seamen to whet and enliven their Courage from theſe Principles, namely, The love of the Reformed Religion, and the Liberties of your Country. The juſtneſs of your Cauſe may make you bold and undaunted, when you engage the Enemies of all that ought to be dear to you; eſpecially if the love of the ſacred Goſpel has its due place in your Hearts. And, O that it had more deep and firm root there! for, a Good Conſcience is as a Wall of Braſs about a Man. <hi>The Righteous is bold as a Lyon, (Prov.</hi> 28. 1.) God has promiſed to put the Fear and Dread of ſuch into the Hearts of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; ſo that they ſhall have a very eaſie Victory, and a very glorious one, becauſe wrought by the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Favour of God. <hi>(Deut.</hi> 11. 25.) <hi>There ſhall no man be able to ſtand before you; for the Lord your God ſhall lay the fear and the dread of you upon all the land that ye ſhall tread upon.</hi> So that you and we have great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to regard the Counſel of God, given, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. 9. <hi>When the Hoſt goeth forth against thine Enemies, then keep thee from every wicked thing.</hi> Wherefore caſt away all Iniquity from you, that ſo the Spirit of the Lord may come mightily upon you, as it did upon the famous Worthies of old, who being thus ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, always did Wonders.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:106807:14"/>
            <p> 5 <hi>Inf.</hi> Let us all (however divided about the leſſer matters of Religion) ſtand up with one Soul againſt the Common Enemies of <hi>Proteſtancy:</hi> And, however unhappily divided we are about ſome Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Notions, let us nevertheleſs, with one conſent, oppoſe the Deſigns of the <hi>Common Enemy</hi> of our Country.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the execrable French Faction here is zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, earneſt, and impudent; daring us publickly with their Wagers, and defying us with their Threats. If in ſuch a Juncture we on the contrary remain cool and indifferent, as if it were a light thing how the matter ſucceeded; we can at this rate make no Countermine to their deſperate Deſigns, but they are too like to carry all before them.</p>
            <p>We have a ſort of ſpiritleſs and enervate Creatures amongſt us, who in a very poor and paſſive manner ſay, <q>We will have no hand one way nor the other; We will not concern our ſelves, nor intermeddle.</q> No, Sirs? what! not when your Enemies come with Idols to your Churches, and Firebrands to your Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes! Not, when a Univerſal Ruine threatens your Selves and Poſterity? Surely, as you will be the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt, ſo will you be the moſt deſpiſed Prey of your Enemies, who (if they have any Manhood in them) will ſhew more Favour to the brave Defenders of their Country, than to the ſneaking Deſerters and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers of it.</p>
            <p>Methinks it might ſufficiently awaken every rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Soul, to puſh on the preſent War with the utmoſt vigour, if he will but exerciſe ſo much Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106807:15"/> as to conſider what will be the dreadful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of miſcarrying in it.</p>
            <p>'Tis to me paſt doubt, that we had better be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by any People in the World than by the <hi>French.</hi> No other Nation has Naval Forces ſufficient to ſecure ſuch a Conqueſt. If the <hi>Turk</hi> ſubdued us, he would miſerably tyrannize; but he would permit us the enjoyment of our Religion for a ſmall yearly Tribute. If other Nations ſubdued us, either their diſtance would ſlacken our Bonds, or their weakneſs would preſs us more lightly <note n="*" place="margin">As in the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts.</note>. But <hi>France</hi> is our next Neighbour, very powerful by Sea and Land, able to load us with heavy Chains, and to rivet them upon us. And beſides, it looks upon us as a Nation capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of being a Rival to her Glory; and has often felt the power of our Arms in her own Bowels: Yea, ſhe has been made a Conqueſt by us, and longs to wipe off that ſtain, and to pull her Lillies out of the Paw of our Lyon. And further, She has often found us a Goad in her Side, when ſhe flew at the Quarry of other Conqueſts. And 'twas only whilſt we ſlept, that She got up ſuch a Fleet upon the Sea, and enlarged her Boundaries ſo widely upon the Land. And upon theſe accounts we muſt expect no Mercy at her hands; but to be ſtript of all our Strength and Glory, and to be made a Dunghil of Deſolation. Her Stateſmen would allow our Liberties no more Quarter, than the Jeſuits would our Religion.</p>
            <p>Ah! how dreadful an infatuation is it, not to be ſenſible of the Approaches of ſuch Miſeries! the meer poſſibility of which, were enough to ſtartle any Man of Senſe, the likelihood of it enough to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106807:15"/> tranſport the meekeſt Spirit into an extreme Rage.</p>
            <p>Should ſuch a Thing come to paſs (which God in mercy for ever avert) what would Poſterity ſay of the Politicks and Proweſs of our preſent Age? What a burning ſhame would the Slavery of <hi>England</hi> be to the preſent Inhabitants of ſo Strong, ſo Rich, and Populous a Land? A Nation ſo much fam'd and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in times paſt all over the World: and ſuch a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Terror to the <hi>French</hi> Nation, where the very Name of an Engliſh-man has been known to get a Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note n="*" place="margin">Witneſs the Tremendous Name of <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot,</hi> in Sir <hi>Ric. Baker</hi>'s Chron.</note> Surely we had, every Soul of us, better dye in the Defence, than live in the Bondage and Reproach of our Nation. I am not over-prone to put men upon the hazzard of their Lives, nor am I raſh in what I have ſpoken; for I again affirm, That our Lives ought to be leſs dear to us than the enjoyment of the Goſpel and the Liberties of our Country. And in this, I am ſure, The Hands and Hearts of all good Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and true Engliſh-men will concur with me.</p>
            <p>For my part, I ſpeak nothing here in Envy or Enmity, to ſo great a Monarch as the French King, I wiſh he really were as great a Heroe as his Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers on both ſides the Sea boaſt him to be. I wiſh he had manifeſted that Truth and Honour in all his promiſes to his own Nation, and Compacts with others, which might render his name Honourable and his Memory bleſſed. O that he never had drawn forth his Sword againſt the Truths of Jeſus Chriſt; nor ſhed the blood of Martyrs in his own Land, and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of blood of poor Innocents in his uſurpations upon the Territories of others. And in ſhort, I ſincerely wiſh, that he were as good a Prince, and Reigned
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106807:16"/> within his juſt dominions with as much Honour and univerſal proſperity as humane Life admits.</p>
            <p>And if theſe were his only Aims, no Good Man would ſtir his Tongue or Hand againſt him. But when he flies at All, without ſenſe of Right, or Bowels of Pity; and would crumble all the Nations of the Earth to Duſt, to erect a Mountainous <hi>Babel</hi> to his own exorbitant Ambition; here 'tis every ones Duty and Intereſt, to do all they can to oppoſe the grand Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſtop the Chaſe of the mighty <hi>Nimrod.</hi> And to excite every Soul to this, I ſhall only add,</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the manifeſt Duty of ſo doing will bind eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">Motives.</note> ſenſible Conſcience; namely, The plain natural Duty of Love to our Country and Religion. To be wanting in this, is to deny the Faith, and act more barbarouſly than Infidels, (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 8.) It is indeed <note place="margin">Neſcio qua na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale ſolum dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedine cunctos ducit, &amp;c.</note> to fight againſt Nature it ſelf, and the God of Nature, who ſeems to inſpire all men with a ſort of fondneſs to their Native Place; ſo that moſt People like their own Home above other places, much finer and better. And this natural Kindneſs ſeems mutual; for the place in which we were bred and born is thought by Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians to abound with ſuch a friendly Air to us, as to be our laſt Relief in time of pineing Sickneſs, when all their other Arts and Drugs are inſufficient to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour us: And ſhall we forſake the Land of our Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in her Extremities, which is ſo cheriſhing and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to us, even to the Death? In this, even inanimate Nature it ſelf will reproach us.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Honour of ſo doing will conſtrain all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Character and Reputation. <hi>Naaman</hi> is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Scripture to have been an Honourable Perſon,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106807:16"/> becauſe by him God had given Deliverance to <hi>Syria;</hi> (2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 5. 1.) And 'tis ſaid, That <hi>Mordecai</hi> was great among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and accepted of the multitude of his Brethren, becauſe he ſought the Wealth of his People. <hi>(Eſth.</hi> 10. 3.) And we behold Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> with Tears proteſting, That ſhe could not endure to ſee the Evil that was coming upon her People, and therefore ſhe put her Life in her Hand to prevent it. <hi>(Eſth.</hi> 8. 6.)</p>
            <p>And our Excellent Queen, of fragrant and bleſſed Memory, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> often aſſured her People, That ſhe was ready to ſacrifice her Life for their Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and acted always as ſhe ſaid, and is therefore to this day had in the greateſt admiration.</p>
            <p>Theſe were Worthies indeed, to be had in everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remembrance! when the lying Statues of ſuch Princes as are only great in doing Evil, will be buried in the Duſt, or rather in the Dunghil.</p>
            <p>O, that all perfidious Betrayers of their Country were treated as their Brother the late Governor of <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delburgh,</hi> and had their Swords broken over their Heads, and the pieces of them thrown in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; which ſurely is more fit, than that they ſhould ſheath them in their Mother's Bowels: And this would be but a very mild, though a very ſymbolical Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch an unnatural Tranſgreſſion.</p>
            <p>But if they eſcape Puniſhment from thoſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray, they will certainly find it at the Hands of thoſe they oblige; their Wooden Shooes will reproach their Blockiſh Heads, and their extreme Folly will not fail to be its own Penance.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Laſtly, The abſolute neceſſity of ſeeking the Good of our Nation in order to our own ſafety and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, will compel all People of Senſe to their Duty
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106807:17"/> of this kind. We muſt be true to the Intereſts of our Country, or periſh in the neglect of the neceſſary Care for our own Safety.</p>
            <p>So that, as we have any natural Love for our Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or any ſupernatural Affection for our Religion, or any natural inſtinct of Self-preſervation, or any ſenſe of Honour in acting ſuitably to all theſe Obligations, we muſt ſeek the Good of our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in its Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical and Civil Rights and Immunities.</p>
            <p>In ſumme, As we would not ſee our Native Country a baſe tributary Province, ſtripp'd of all its Glory, and made ſervile to a Foreign Power: As we would not deliver up our Children to be bred up in the Deluſions of Popery, and be the means of their Slavery to the moſt Arbitrary and Cruel Maſters: As we would not behold our Enemies reaping what we have ſown, and inhabiting the Houſes that we have built: And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as we would not behold the Altars of Superſtition ſet up in our Churches, nor ſuffer the Light of the Goſpel (for which our Martyrs dyed) to be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd by the <hi>Abomination that maketh deſolate:</hi> I ſay, as we would ſhun theſe intolerable Plagues, and longer enjoy thoſe ineſtimable Bleſſings (ſpiritual and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral) which we now are bleſt withal, we muſt all do our utmoſt to caſt away all Iniquity from us, and to ſue out our Peace with God, through our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> And withal, we muſt unanimouſly apply our utmoſt Induſtry, to withſtand the vigorous Efforts of our powerful Enemies: as we have any tenderneſs for our Brethren and Companions, or any Zeal for the Houſes of the Lord our God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſider what has been ſaid, and the Lord give you Underſtanding in all things.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
